I create content for a living. My niche
is digital [music] writing. And in that
niche, I write short form posts on X. I
make carousels on LinkedIn. I spend a
bunch of money making videos like this
on YouTube and Instagram, [music] which
is how I've generated over $6 million in
revenue this year and over $20 million
in lifetime revenue in the past 5 years.
So, if you're still trying to find your
niche as a content creator, especially
if you want your niche to be lucrative,
then this video is for you. I'm going to
walk you through my entire process for
discovering your niche as a content
creator in any industry, no matter how
you want to monetize. Finding my niche
in digital writing is how our business
went on to generate over $20 million in
lifetime sales. This year, we did over 6
million in revenue. And it's been
incredibly lucrative and it's not that
big of a niche. And so, no, you don't
need some giant niche or industry in
order to make money. You could pick the
most obscure niche in the world and I
will show you how to monetize it.
So, before we talk about how to find
your niche, we need to break down a
couple faulty beliefs because every time
I explain this, people always hit me
with these same questions and same
objections. So, I want to walk you
through it because I think it'll help
prime you to understand how to go about
finding your niche. So, the first faulty
belief is people think if I pick a
niche, I can never change it. Okay? They
think of it like a marriage decision.
And this is not true. Okay? My niche
today is digital writing. The first
niche that I played in back in 2013 was
fitness. And the first product that I
created was an ebook series called
Skinny to Shredded. Okay? So, you
probably don't know that or you never
knew that. And that's okay. That's the
point. Your niche can change. All right?
This is not a marriage decision. And if
anything, you will learn more by picking
a niche and sticking with it for a year,
two years, three years. Because when you
go deep in a niche, you have to learn
and build all the other skills in order
to make that niche successful.
successful for you. Once you build those
skills, you can apply those skills to
any niche. And I always like proving it
with a really simple example. Imagine if
I said to you, "Hey, I'm happy to write
all your content and create all your
products for you for free. Would you
like me to do that?" You would probably
say, "Yeah, Cole, I would love for you
to do that, but I know nothing about
your niche. I know nothing about your
industry." you would probably still
trust me or want my help because you see
that I have done all these things in my
niche and you assume that I could use
those skills in your niche too. Okay, so
yes, these are things that you can use
for the rest of your career.
Now, the second faulty belief that
you've probably internalized or maybe
you've heard this by seeing other
content on the internet is, well, I
think my niche is me, right? I am the
niche. That is wrong. Okay, you are not
the niche. And I can prove it with a
very simple example. Real quick, if you
want to write online but aren't sure
where to start, click the link in the
description of this video and check out
startwritingline.com.
This is a free master class I put
together sharing all of our most helpful
frameworks for beginners, like proven
hooks to capture your target reader
attention, [music] where to write online
to get the most distribution on your
work, and little growth hacking tips to
build your social audience and email
list faster. Over a 100,000 writers have
gone through this free master class and
many even send us emails afterwards
thanking us for sharing such valuable
information for free. So click the link
below this video to check it out and
make this year the year you start seeing
success from your writing online. Let's
say that uh we're hanging out one Friday
night and I go, "Hey, do you want to go
to Larry's for dinner?" You go, "I don't
know. What kind of food does Larry
serve?" I go, "Don't worry about what
food it serves. Larry's is incredible.
They've won all these awards. Uh, it's
it's amazing. Just trust me. You go,
"Yeah, I don't really care how many
awards they've won. I want to know, does
Larry serve sushi or pizza?" Right? That
is a category question. You don't care
about the brand, aka me. You care about
the category. Because I might say,
"Larry's is an amazing restaurant." But
if I go, "Yeah, Larry's is pizza." And
you go, "Ah, I just had pizza last
night. I'm really not in the mood. I
want sushi." That is a category
decision. It has nothing to do with the
brand. It has everything to do with the
category. So, when you're looking for a
niche, your niche is not about you. It's
not about your personal interests. Your
niche is this intersection between what
you care about and what other people
care about. This is you. This is other
people. You're looking for this in the
middle, right? You don't want to pick
something that other people care about,
but you're not interested in at all.
Right? And you also don't want to pick
something that only has to do with your
interest, but no one else cares about,
right? You're looking for that overlap.
And when you discover that overlap, the
the point of that overlap is the niche
is about the other person. It's about
their interests. It's about their
questions. It's about the problems they
have in their life. It's about the
outcomes that they're trying to
generate. And when you focus on that,
it's very easy to create content because
you know exactly who you're creating
for.
Which leads to the third faulty belief.
If I niche down, I will have no
opportunity. there won't be enough
people for me to help. This is probably
one of the biggest misunderstandings
that people have about this idea of
niching down. If you've ever read the
book uh positioning by Al Reese and Jack
Trout, it's an iconic marketing book.
Everyone should read it. The big idea in
that book is that when you say you do
everything, no one can hear you. No one
can understand you. When you say you do
one very specific thing, everyone
assumes that you can also help them.
Okay? So, let me give you a really basic
example. Let's say that I go out into
the world and I say, "Hey, I can help
you with writing."
That is an extremely broad category,
right? Are we talking about speech
writing? Are we talking about newsletter
writing? Are we talking about short form
content writing? Are we talking about
blog post writing? Are we talking about
thought leadership writing? Are we
talking about press release writing?
What kind of writing are we talking
about? We're talking about fiction
writing, right? As a result, when I say
something this broad, nobody can hear
me. Nobody knows where to put me in
their brain, right? But if I say, I
ghost write, just for example, I ghost
write LinkedIn content for SAS founders.
All of a sudden, I have niched down and
this person can hear me very clearly.
But you know who else I attract? I also
attract other founders and I attract
other people in SAS and I attract anyone
who wants to write on LinkedIn. So when
you get more specific, what actually
happens is all of these people around
the person that you're targeting also
assume that you can help them too. Every
founder assumes that your skills will
translate to them. Everyone in SAS
assumes that your skills will translate
to them. Everyone who wants to create
content on LinkedIn assumes your skills
will translate to them. And then it
doesn't stop there. It goes beyond there
because if you work with founders, why
can't you help CEOs and other execs,
right? Why can't you help department
heads?
Everyone assumes that you could also
help them. If you could help SAS, why
can't you do B2B tech,
right? If you if you could help them on
LinkedIn, why can't you also help them
on X? Why can't you also help them on
Instagram? Why can't you also help them
writing YouTube captions or YouTube
descriptions? Everyone else assumes that
you can also help them. So, it's a it's
a logical fallacy thinking. If I niche
down, I limit my opportunity. No, what
you're actually doing is you're making
it easier for everyone to understand
what to do with you. If you lead with
something really broad, no one knows
where to put you. That's why it's a
problem. Hey, by the way, if you're
brand new to the world of ghostwriting,
maybe you've heard the term but aren't
really sure what it is or how it's
[music] different from copywriting or
content writing. Check out premium
ghostwritingbloopprint.com. It's in the
description below. Okay, this is a free
master class that I've put together for
writers who want to monetize their
skills and love for writing with
ghostriting. This is what I [music] did
and ghostriting completely changed my
life. It's how I quit my job. It's how I
quadrupled the amount of money I was
making. It's how I've gotten to work
with so many smart, amazing people, but
also have time for my own writing, like
writing this book, The Art and Business
of Ghostwriting. Anyways, check it out.
If you're at all interested in making
money from your writing, I would really
encourage you to get into ghost writing.
And this free premium ghost writing
blueprint in the description below is
the best place to start.
Okay, so you understand why niching down
actually helps you tap into more
opportunity. But let me explain why
niching down also makes you so much
money. Okay? And I always like starting
with this uh really basic story. So
imagine that you just bought this
beautiful house and you know you have
this really pretty stained glass window
right above the front door and one day
your neighbor's idiot kid fires a hockey
puck through the window and the stained
glass window shatters and you need to
find someone to fix it. Okay. So what do
you do? You go on the internet and you
start looking for someone who can repair
the window. Now, again, this is a really
pretty stained glass window. This isn't
your average window. All right. Which
window repair person are you going to
hire? Are you going to hire the first
one that says, "I repair windows. Any
window you need, I can repair it." Or
are you going to hire the person who
says, "I specialize in stained glass
windows." Right? You are going to pick
the second person every single time
because you have a very specific problem
and you're looking for someone who
specializes in that specific problem.
Okay? Everyone thinks if I go broad, if
I say I do everything for everyone, I
will attract more opportunity. It is the
complete opposite. The more specific you
get about what problem you solve or what
outcome you drive, the more likely you
are to get that specific person to want
to hire you. And then again going back
to what I just explained, you also tap
into all the other people who go, "Oh,
well, if you specialize in that, I
assume that you could also bring that
specialty over to my problem as well."
Now, there are three reasons that
niching down makes you so much money.
Okay? So, the first one is pricing
power. When you specialize, you become
the go-to person for that niche, that
industry, that problem, that outcome.
All right? When you are the go-to
person, you actually have no
competition, right? All the general
window repair people, they're all
competing against each other. They all
say, "I do everything. I do everything.
Let me know what you need." The stained
glass window repair person goes, "I
specialize in this one thing. If you're
looking for a specialist, let me know."
Fundamentally, that means that you
differentiate yourself from any and all
competition. Okay? So, it gives you
pricing power. This is the first reason
why niching down is so effective.
The second reason is efficiency. Now,
you might not realize this right away,
but this is especially true if you have
a service business. So, for example, uh
I've spent a lot of my career writing
for other people as a ghostwriter. I
started working just for myself. Then I
turned my my service into a whole
ghostwriting agency. I have made a lot
of money by writing for other people.
That's providing a service. It's very
hard to create efficiencies when the
service that you're providing is
anything, right? How are you going to
create efficiencies if one client wants
blog posts and another client wants
Instagram captions and another client
wants newsletters and every client is in
a different industry? Think about the
switching cost, right? You're writing
different things for different people in
different industries. That's very hard.
The way that you build efficiency is by
doing the same thing over and over and
over again. So for me, that was thought
leadership articles for CEOs. This was
the only thing that we did. It was 800
words. We didn't do newsletters. We
didn't do short form content. We didn't
manage your your LinkedIn page. The only
thing that we did was write thought
leadership articles around 800 words for
founders and sea level executives. It's
the only thing we did. And we scaled
that to hundreds of pieces every single
month. 20 plus full-time employees, 2
million plus in annual revenue. Okay? 80
plus clients around the world at any
given time. So whenever people say, "Oh
no, that limits my opportunity. That
limits my ability to make money." No.
The more specific that you get, the more
efficiency you can build. And the reason
this is so important is because if you
have no efficiency, maybe you could work
with three clients. If you have
efficiency, maybe you could work with
10. When you have efficiencies, this
allows you to make way more money. Okay?
So that's the big idea here is it
actually allows you to increase your
capacity which means you can take on
more work.
And so the third reason is revenue. If
you have pricing power that means that
you dominate a niche, right? You are the
go-to person. I became the go-to person
for thought leadership articles. Go
written for founders and executives.
That allows you to charge more and more.
When you're able to have pricing power
and you double down on a very specific
niche, a very specific service, that
allows you to create efficiency. Okay?
Efficiency is how you templatize the
work that you do, which means you can
get more done in less time. So, you
could choose to make more money or you
could just focus on reclaiming time,
right? Maybe you don't want to work
eight hours a day. Maybe you're cool
with the amount of money that you're
making, but you can get it done in four
hours a day, right? So, you could get
paid in time. Or third, you can increase
your capacity which increases revenue.
So now the same person or the same, you
know, group of people, the same team,
instead of servicing just three clients,
you could service 10.
Instantly, your situation becomes three
times more profitable, five times more
profitable, right? And so niching down
is how you accomplish these benefits. If
you don't niche down, what happens is
you're a generalist and you have no
pricing power and you have no
efficiency, which means you have no
ability to either reclaim time or
increase revenue. That's why so many
people get stuck, writers especially.
So I want to end this with a little bit
of tough love and a brutal truth that I
have learned over the years. Okay. The
brutal truth is that the reason people
bounce from niche to niche and they
never take the time to specialize or
learn any of these skills is because it
is significantly easier to change niches
than it is to be confronted with the
fact that you lack the skills, the other
tangental skills to make a niche work.
Okay? Because if you niche down, what do
you have to learn how to do? Well, you
have to learn how to create content.
This is how you're going to attract
opportunities. You need to learn how to
maybe create a little funnel for
yourself, maybe a newsletter, maybe an
educational email course, capture some
emails. You need to learn how to run a
sales call, right? You're never going to
attract premium opportunities if you're
just sitting on Upwork or Fiverr waiting
for someone to tell you what to do,
right? You need to get comfortable
running projects and being a project
manager.
You need to learn these skills. And so
what happens is someone picks a niche
and then they get confronted with these
different new skills that they have to
build and they get overwhelmed and they
go actually you know what would be way
easier is if I blame the niche and I
just go try and do something different
and then you start right back at level
one all over again and you repeat this
cycle over and over and over again and
you don't realize that every time you
change niches you run into the same
brick
the same problems. These are never going
away. These will always be there no
matter what niche you pick. And I I run
into this, you know, I mentor over a
thousand writers in our premium ghost
writing academy. I have answered this
question and explained this 500 times
and I see it over and over again,
especially with beginners. It's fine. I
just want to be honest about it. Is
beginners think that the answer is
picking a different niche, picking a
different industry, and that's not the
answer. The answer is confronting the
fact that you lack these other skills
and you would be way better off in the
long term caring less about the niche
and just committing to using this as a
vehicle to build a bunch of these other
skills.
Okay, so let's end with tactically how
do you go about finding your niche?
Right? This this is something that
people really build up in their heads. I
think they make it very existential.
They tell themselves, you know, that the
niche that I pick is going to represent
me for the rest of my life. No, it's not
a marriage decision. It's not that
serious. The beginner version of how you
find a niche for you is very simple. You
create 30 pieces of content in 30 days.
You create something every single day.
This idea is what caused our beginner
writing program, Ship 30 for30, to grow
so quickly. Okay, we had north of 10,000
people go through this. It was a very
simple idea. You're not creating. You
should be creating. Why don't we ship 30
pieces of content in 30 days? You will
gather a bunch of data. You will learn
what works
throughout this process. You're going to
notice at the end of every week, every
two weeks, at the end of the 30 days,
you're going to notice, hey, it's
actually these two or three topics that
are getting the most distribution that
people are enjoying the most. Okay? It's
a very simple idea. Now, where people go
wrong and the problem here is what they
think they're looking for is, oh, I
wrote 30 pieces, you know, all of them
got one like, two likes, three likes,
you know, 10 views, 50 views, 100 views,
and they're looking for an outlier in
the extreme sense. They think, oh, I'm
looking for the post that gets a million
views. That's not how it works,
especially in the beginning. These two
or three winning topics are usually only
like 2x better than everything else. So,
if you write 30 pieces, maybe everything
gets two likes, but these few, maybe
they got four likes. You You might think
that's not that big of a difference, but
it's a huge difference. That's twice as
good, right? So, what should you do? You
go, "Oh, actually, these two or three
topics, they actually performed twice as
good as everything else, three times
better, five times better." What do you
do the next 30 days? You double down.
You take what's working and you do it
again. you go, let me write about those
two or three topics over and over and
over again, right? Let me write about
the same topic for a different audience.
Let me write about the same topic, but
it solves a slightly different problem.
It generates a slightly different
outcome, right? At the end of the 30
days, what do you do? You go back and
you look for the two to three,
that's messy. Two to three different
topics. Maybe it's the same topics, but
you look at the data again. You go, "Oh,
those started performing better. Maybe
they performed twice as good. Let me do
that again." And this is what you do
every 30 days over and over and over and
over and over again. If you look at your
favorite creator, your favorite author,
your favorite YouTuber, your favorite
person on LinkedIn, all of them are
doing this process. I still do this
process every week, every two weeks,
every month. I go back through and I go,
"Hey, that post performed pretty well. I
should do it again. I should write about
that topic again." This is a very simple
strategy, but it requires you to start.
It requires you to actually be putting
out volume in order to see what works.
The advanced strategy is once you learn,
okay, these are the two to three topics
that I see performing really well. You
create what I like to call your client
constellation.
Now, if you're providing a writing
service, you can use the word client. If
you're not and you just want to create
digital products, you might call this
your content constellation. Okay, this
idea is very simple, but it's really
cool. It's something I noticed most
people don't realize. By the way, if
you're brand new to writing online and
want a really easy place to start, I
recommend reading The Art and Business
of Online Writing. I wrote this book
after I'd been writing online for over a
decade and accumulated over a billion
views on my work, monetizing my writing
in all sorts of unconventional ways. And
I [music] wrote this book to give other
writers like you a way to skip all the
lessons that I had to learn the hard way
and start seeing success from your
writing a whole lot faster than I did.
[music] So if writing online is
something you're thinking about or
something you're actively practicing, I
recommend picking up a copy of The Art
and Business of Online Writing. I could
talk about non-fiction
and fiction.
I could talk about ghostwriting.
I could talk about copywriting.
This is an umbrella and all you have to
do is realize that inside of this
umbrella are lots of other relevant
subcategories. Okay, but again going
back to our big idea from one of the
best books on marketing I've ever read,
positioning by Al Reese and Jack Trout.
Okay, if you lead with everything, no
one can hear you. If you lead with one
thing, everyone can hear you. If I lead
with digital writing, everyone can hear
me. But I don't have to just write about
digital writing. I'm just leading with
that. That's just the tip of the spear.
But I can still write about
self-publishing and non-fiction and
fiction and ghostwriting and
copywriting. That is what builds your
constellation. And if you're building
digital products, that's a content
constellation. And if you're providing
writing services, that's a client
constellation. I actually talk about all
these ideas in my two bestselling books,
The Art and Business of Ghostwriting and
The Art and Business of Online Writing.
So, if you want to go deep on all of
this stuff, how to find your niche, how
to create a content strategy, how to
write content that goes viral, all
right, how to get paid, how to monetize
your writing talents with a service,
these books are a really great uh place
to start. So, I would encourage you to
grab these. But otherwise, you know,
this is how it works. Don't over
complicate it. You have to get moving in
order to test and gather data and see
what's working, what's resonating with
readers. And then as you clarify what
topics or topic you want to be your
niche, you're not limited. It [music]
becomes a constellation. You can tap
into as many other relevant
subcategories as you want.